[Music]
hey folks
welcome to the dark horse podcast live
stream our 18th i am sitting with dr
heather heing
and we are going to talk to you today
about why it is that we are so confused
about covet 19
and what we are supposed to be doing
about it
are you ready to embark on that
discussion i am all right
so let's talk about what we are seeing
um
in the world and you know we are all
seeing
the world through this lens that is
social media and i have to say one of
the
lessons of all of this i suspect is that
um
social media has become the ghost in our
machine
and on the one hand that may sound
nonsensical because we can see what
social media is but the algorithms
themselves
obviously haunt our thinking in ways
that we
can't even test are you suggesting the
pandemic has
made social media into more of a ghost
in the machine or that it has merely
revealed it
more stark relief yeah i think because
nobody has a real
handle on this because it is emerging in
real time
we are seeing something about the
magnitude of its effect
and we have talked about uh phenomena
that you cannot detect directly
but that you can detect as gravity you
know so
for example um the existence of a planet
that manifests first not
as our ability to see a planet but its
effect on
other planets in their orbits we can
estimate how big the effect is and i
think
uh we are seeing something here of
extraordinary magnitude
and it's to be honest with you not very
hopeful
um but what exactly it is and why it
works the way it does
is less clear yeah because it is hidden
in a a literally private layer
it's the ultimate black box in a sense
yeah so it's interesting
listening to you talk it it seems like
you could be talking about
the algorithms in social media as the
ghost in the machine
and not so much that goes to the machine
but so much of what you just said
actually could apply equally to what
this virus
is and how it's doing what it's doing in
various layers in society
well i mean i think these things are and
you know we've said from the beginning
that these are two very different things
there's the hazard of the virus and then
there's the hazard of its effect on us
and at the moment as concerned as i am
about the virus
i'm much more concerned about what we're
going to do to each other as we attempt
to sort out
uh issues of social distancing and mask
wearing and the like
yup um i actually start by uh
by reading from uh so this is excellent
essay in this month's or
the june episode of harper's uh thomas
chariton williams who is a
terrific thinker and writer for those of
you who don't know him an essay called
reading the plague in quarantine the
plague being camus
1947 i think it is novel
um and here's just here's a quote from
the plague itself translated from the
french
a pestilence isn't a thing made to man's
measure therefore we tell ourselves that
pestilence is a mere bogey of the mind a
bad dream that will pass away
but it doesn't always pass away our
townsfolk were not more to blame than
others they forgot to be modest that was
all
and thought that everything still was
possible for them which presupposed the
pestilences were impossible
they went on doing business arranged for
journeys and formed views
how should they have given a thought to
anything like plague which rules out any
future
cancels journeys silences the exchange
of views
and then one more thing there's a few
more in here but just for right now
williams writes camus was clear and
careful throughout in his presentation
of what it takes to combat the forces of
annihilation
quote there's no question of heroism in
all this he writes
it's a matter of common decency that's
an idea that may make some people smile
but the only means of fighting a plague
is common decency
it's a matter of common decency the only
way of fighting a plague is common
decency this is this is
beautiful so i think then the natural
thing to do is to take a look at the two
clips that we
found circulating online about the way
these clips happen to be from the us
about the way some americans are
treating other americans in light of
covid19 so let's
let's start with the one that i believe
was circulating
earlier um i think i've only seen one
that you're talking about yeah that's
since we're dealing with a different
texture
so uh the multiple clips stitched
together
yep
i think that's not the one oh yeah what
was that where she
have some sound thank you for coughing
bye
well we don't know if you can hear this
in
your position but what we have
wow are americans
coughing at each other in retail
environments
[Music]
oh she's fitting i got it
okay
we have assault and battery
i work for costco and i'm asking this
member to put on our ass because that is
our company policy
so either wear the map and i'm not doing
this i woke up in a free country
all right before we discuss what we've
just seen here i would like to show the
other
clip that was circulating this week
so here this is a clip from staten
island
[Music]
those of you who can't see it we have a
woman not wearing a mask in the grocery
store
being shamed and chased out of the
grocery store by
a bunch of patrons wearing masks
so i think we have to be very careful
addressing this question i am
aware that i have some sympathies
somewhere in here but that they do not
amount to a simple analysis of either
clip
my reaction is that this is us going
insane
and that i believe i can detect in my
own
processing of what i'm hearing and
seeing and reading
that i'm struggling to stay above
water i'm trying to tread water fast
enough that i don't
uh succumb to some overly simple
position but that that struggle has
become difficult and i think a lot of
people are just simply
failing at it and that this is the
product
it manifests as fed up at best
and excruciating and perhaps angry
and you know almost demonic at worst
yeah it is um almost demonic is not a
bad description
i would say the thing that strikes me
most is
let's take covet 19 out of the situation
let's say that we were somehow
dealing with the common cold the idea
that somebody would deliberately
cough at somebody else sick or not
but just to suggest the possibility of
transmitting a cold to somebody who
didn't have it
that would be a monstrous act because
the amount of harm that even something
as minor as the common cold
carries with it is a major setback in a
life
right it's a week or two of misery who
knows how many people are downstream of
you when you have one of these things
hopefully you can not transmit it to
anyone else
but it you know who knows how many
people
some cold that you have had has passed
from you to many
so the amount of misery in one misplaced
cough
is potentially large and yet these
people are playing at it
cold isn't as bad as the flu and the flu
isn't as bad as cove at 19. and by bad
the simplest metric as we've talked
about here before
is deaths colds don't kill people unless
those people have a considerable number
of
comorbidities underlying conditions you
know things have to be going very very
badly for someone for a cold to kill
them
flus do kill people and copen19 is
clearly killing people
but the long-term effects
as i don't remember which number it was
but you talked at some length in one of
our earlier live streams
about um it was the one we were talking
about um
telomeres about imagining
what it is that is pulling you to the
grave and that every
sickness insult injury that you get
contributes just a little bit to making
you
a bit less robust a bit more prone to
future
injury and insult and illness and it
shortens the
literally shortens the lifespan of the
cell lines that have been injured
right like it actually just literally
does that and each of your cell lines is
not the same as your individual life
but without a significant number of your
cell lines you cannot continue to live
and this is of course what senescence is
yeah it's you know it's like a video
game in which you have some quantity of
life force and things spend it and to
have another
citizen even ingest
approach you with something that robs
you of some of your
most precious element your the life
force that keeps you around
is ghastly and to do it in the context
of a pandemic that i promise you nobody
completely understands
i mean really we don't know what this
bug
is capable of we don't know what it will
become
we don't know what it is all of those
things are still open
questions have anybody playing with this
thing
or feeling so sure of their position
that they are entitled
to um you know
again i keep saying ingest it's not
really ingest given that
many people have this uh disease without
showing any symptoms
these people who are coughing may well
be sick especially if they've been lacks
about masks which they obviously have
now on the other hand we've got this
other clip
where people are chasing a woman who's
not wearing a mask
out of a store i don't know for sure
whether the store
had a requirement but um
again it's not that i'm without some
sympathy
for their position here there there is a
thing in the absence of governance
there's a thing
that keeps people behaving honorably and
it has to do
with reputation and it has to do with
people willing to penalize those who
misbehave and so
there's an ancient tradition here on the
other hand
uh this woman whoever she is
i'm certain she arrived at this position
that she was safe to be in this grocery
store without a mask
because she's been fed bad information
she's not the villain here and she's
being
chased out of this grocery store as if
she's a terrible human being
um now if one of those people who
coughed on somebody were chased out
by people in masks um i think
i think i would get it and i think i
would accept it but assuming that didn't
happen here
my sense is you're still turning on
another citizen who's as confused as you
are
right yeah well there we've been handed
a lot of simple rubrics some of which
contradict one another
some of which have changed over time
like you know as we talked about i think
in our very first
live stream here the surgeon general of
the united states and the who were both
saying masks don't wear masks they do
you no good
uh before they both reversed completely
so
similarly and this isn't exactly the
same kind of thing but
one of the things that's being done as
places begin to open up at least in
areas in the u.s that i'm aware of
is that in some in some kinds of
establishments that are opening up
they are doing temperature checks at the
door
and this strikes me as
mostly ridiculous because most people it
seems according to
our current and mostly like all the way
back in our understanding of this
particular disease
are asymptomatic and are spreading the
thing even if they become symptomatic
are most infectious um or at least quite
infectious before they develop any
symptoms at all
so the asymptomatic and the
pre-symptomatic asymptomatic and the
pre-symptomatic are both capable of
spreading disease
the the never exposed are obviously not
capable of spreading disease because
they do not have it
but presymptomatic and asymptomatic are
both terms that refer to people who
have the disease are capable of
spreading it or
are have the disease in them and
taking people's temperatures seems like
a pacifying move
a way to make people feel like they're
doing something like they're being
active and it's not going it is actually
going to give people a false sense of
security
and i worry that many of the people
who are engaged in flaunting the rules
are reading are hearing
wear masks and take your temperature and
stay indoors as similar sorts of rubrics
that all make no sense and of course the
first one
does make sense from an epidemiological
perspective wear masks when you are
in stores with strangers or with or in
close proximity to other people
whom you do not know the health history
of
do you know take people's temperatures
at every moment possible
and have the sense then that if they
don't have an elevated temperature at
the moment then they're healthy
no they're not necessarily healthy now
if they do have an elevated temperature
you know something maybe but you also
don't know if they have covered 19 then
we have something else
yeah although in a world where
we all got the same software update so
we all understood what the implications
of a temperature being taken
was i could see it as one piece
of a much larger strategy in other words
how many illnesses could you prevent
if everybody whose temperature was
elevated at the point they wanted to
enter a place
was barred obviously it doesn't bar the
people who are completely asymptomatic
or completely pre-symptomatic
but it would stop a certain number
of cases so you have to put up that
savings
against the false sense of security
which actually could kill people
the sense that it's safe enough might be
worse than the benefit
and you know the the behavioral role
which has been
around for decades which is if you're
sick stay home
you know hopefully you you know right
now this doesn't pertain but you know
you
go to a school or you go to you have a
workplace that if you're sick you aren't
going to get penalized for
or calling in sick and staying home and
of course many people don't have that
luxury under normal conditions
but um when people go out into the world
when they are
actively sick they are causing problems
for not just themselves they are not
just extending the life of their own
sickness but they are of course
risking other people and you know people
who have active fevers
uh shouldn't be out there in the first
place and
i i worry actually more about the false
sense of security from
temperature taking stations than i think
the value
will be gained from catching the few
people who have
active fevers at the moment because it
really does see you know it's it's
it's medicalizing of in this case and
obviously
medical process but because it's
because it's a metric because it's it is
an
action done by someone to you and then
you have a number
people love numbers we and in fact i
think that the most enumerable among us
are the most fond of these simple
measures that may not mean what they
what we think they mean
and so i very much worry about the idea
of being out there being told
oh yeah your temperature is fine maybe
that means that they're less likely to
wear a mask
in a crowded store for instance
yeah in some sense i think though if
that's right
and it may well be right it is a
small corner of a big problem
and the big problem is that if there's
one thing we know about sars cove
to and covet 19
it's part of a complex system not only
is the virus itself a part of a complex
system
the body it interfaces with and
therefore the symptomatology
is a complex system the body politic is
a complex system
uh the world economy is a complex system
and all of these things are interfacing
in ways that do not fit our
clearly strong desire to have an
answer am i safe to do x if i were
this am i protected none of these things
have perfectly clear answers
and um that is i think
allowing people to be driven crazy so if
we can i want to
point to two things which again will
harken back to discussions we've had
at various times one
is we have two sources of
bad thinking in the case of this
pandemic
one of those sources is noise this thing
is so new
and the way that it interfaces with the
body is so complex
that there's just false leads everywhere
there are things that appear to be
patterns that weren't patterns or there
were patterns for a moment and then the
pattern evaporated because it was
overwhelmed by some other pattern
this is noise and then we have false
signal
which is frankly even worse than
a systematic bias of an experiment false
signal that's being delivered
by people who have a conflict of
interest and this is the thing that
worries me
above all else is i have the sense that
for a while
americans and in some sense the world
were somewhat galvanized by facing
this very frightening pandemic
as one we were all seeing it for the
first time it was disrupting
almost every life every human life on
earth
and that disruption
caused us all to think because what else
were we going to do yeah
but something took our willingness to
think
and it captured it it's now delivering
us
messages that are not based on our best
understanding of what's going on
they're based on the political advantage
that comes from
pushing one story much farther than any
of the actual evidence suggests
and the question is a
is there any way to avoid this
and b if there's not what is going to
happen when
even covet 19 can't get us to put
our political bias biases and
allegiances
aside i mean we're going to tear each
other apart yeah no and it does feel
like like the u.s is doing a
particularly poor job of this
at least this is this is thomas chariton
williams take and i've seen a few other
places as well
that we are polarizing more fully
than other places and it does seem to
come down to
the classic tension that most people
don't think of as a tension
between freedom or liberty and justice
and
you know we are we are promised both in
this country
right and it is imagined that liberty
and justice are two
of the very few primary ideals of a
democracy that this is what the
government
is supposed to be providing liberty uh
justice
while not uh taking much of your liberty
but we have these sort of caricatures of
these positions right now
on basically on the far left we have
slide it all the way over to maximize
justice freedom be damned liberty be
damned
and on the extreme right we have the
slider all the way to extreme
liberty justice be damned and the idea
of coughing on someone else you are
you are actively taking away the the
rights of other people
and um and you know what's going on
in the sort of no nuance world of we'll
be in locked in full lockdown maybe in
your house
full masks at all time until the end of
time space i don't
i don't really see that but i imagine
it's out there to some degree
um uh also relieves everyone sort of
maximally of their freedom
of their liberty and i was thinking
about this the idea of
with liberty and justice for all of
course is um instantiated in our pledge
of allegiance even which every
school kid in a in a public school
anyway ends up repeating over and over
and over again
um and i didn't realize that it was
actually madison james madison
for whom our dog is named and for whom
the program
which we are um ensconced uh luckily
at princeton is named um so in the i'm
going to read this here the 51st paper
the federalists the federalist papers
james madison says
justice is the end of government it is
the end of civil society by which he
means it's the it's the final state
it ever has but it ever will be pursued
until it be obtained
or until liberty be lost in the pursuit
he points out james madison points out
that there is a trade-off between these
two
and that we are what a democracy is
doing is pursuing liberty
until we start losing freedom but of
course
you could read that by you could read
that at either extreme and
the fact is we we can't do either and
retain
our a civil society we can't we can't
slide
either of these two to their extremes
yeah you can never optimize any one
thing in
any complex system because you'll crash
every other parameter that's important
that's just
the simple consequence but i even find
there's
something odd about the supposed liberty
maximizers
is that i don't think their position has
anything to do with anything
that uh could wisely be called liberty
it's a very
narrow form of liberty am i free to go
to ex-establishment and dress as i like
okay
well if you were really trying to
maximize liberty
then you would have to understand that
somebody else ending up
in the icu has to be counted against
liberty you're not very free if you're
in the icu
so there is always a question about
whether the liberty you are maximizing
is
narrow or whether it is broad
maximizing broad liberty requires
high quality regulation of things if
everybody's free to drive on both sides
of the road
you're not very free to drive anywhere
because you're taking your life into
your hands every time you get behind the
wheel
so we have to limit your freedom to one
side of the road or the other
in order for you to be free to drive
from here to wherever
right that's an excellent example
likewise you know the
massive regulation that surrounds air
travel
right the ability to fly anywhere on
earth i mean that's a huge
boon to freedom it comes from regulation
that's the thing that makes it possible
so anyone who's ever flown has benefited
from regulation
right and you frankly you know you'd
have to be crazy not to want it that way
does that
mean that there are not places where the
regulations go too far
no of course there are and you couldn't
even build a system in which there
wouldn't be excesses
there will be excesses there will be
places where the regulations don't go
far enough
that's noise but the um
the position that has people
rejecting the importance of the virus
and thereby arguing in favor of
basically a return to normalcy right
down to
face coverings not being uh
not only not being required but mocking
people who wear them which is now an
active
feature of the landscape this is absurd
and the thing
the thing that is missing the thing that
increasingly is haunting me
is i don't see a contingent who are
saying
we really have to open back up
that's a very dangerous thing to do the
way to do it
is with extreme caution with respect to
things like
face masks and physical distancing so
instead of you know the position there's
nothing to worry about let's just go
back to normal i would expect to see
people
advocating for let us go back to
economic normalcy
and in order to do that let us behave in
extremely
careful and meticulous fashion with
respect to how
we are around each other what's more
that what i think is
i mean i don't think that is my position
i think actually it's not time to go
back to normalcy yet because the danger
is still too great and the unknowns are
still too large but i understand the
perspective
and yet you see almost no one occupying
the position i see almost no one
occupying the position and that tells me
something is not right here
what's more and you and i have been on
this uh from the beginning
there are places where actually
the nature of covet 19 as we see it in
may of 2020
is such that we could afford more
liberty so to the extent that there are
places where we actually have to curtail
liberty right now for the greater good
there are places we can afford to relax
it so i would expect to see
a intelligent synthetic
position that said look outside for
reasons we don't yet understand
you're way safer than we thought okay
outside is pretty safe so let's take
advantage of that side what does that
mean clock's ticking
in the northern hemisphere where most of
us live
summer is about to dawn it's not going
to last forever vitamin d is an
important component
so let us take advantage of outdoors let
us let us ratchet up
our return to normalcy outdoors as much
as we can
but i would say if you're engaged in an
activity that makes it difficult to wear
a mask if you're biking hard if you're
running hard
probably you don't want to be wearing a
mask we went out for a family bike ride
the other day a long one
15 miles into town that involves quite a
few hills
quite a few hills we had masks with us
we wore them if we were near people but
as we were riding hard we weren't we
didn't have them over our mouths don't
think any of us ever put them
on while we're biking not while we were
riding but when we were
stopped and there were people um but
in any case so you can make a judgment
call there
um but what i you know again i think the
intelligent position would have to
recognize
not only is sars cove 2 a virus
with unknown capacities but it's also an
evolving
virus right if we give it the
opportunity to spread
outside then it will probably go from
being very difficult to spread outside
to figuring out how to do it and then we
will lose that opportunity so we should
protect it we should cherish it
but i don't see this position and what
that tells me is that
the opportunity for us to become
enlightened about this terrible thing
that has happened to planet earth
is being lost in favor of some
mind-numbing and terrifying political
instinct
to do i mean these people who are
coughing on other people
they are clearly not seeing the other
person
as human this is what people do before
they go to war
against people they dehumanize them and
in this case we are
watching it happen you know they are
willing to spread a pathogen to somebody
because
not spreading it to them is not
important how terrifying is that that
americans would do that to each other
no no this is this is the drum beat that
that we've been on that this is not the
moment uh
to choose sides on the basis of how
someone has voted or how someone is
going to vote or what party they're in
and you know as we've said in previous
live streams
if if trump begins to act like a
statesman
uh we all need to get behind him and
if uh if if he doesn't
then people should not be blindly
following him
because they liked him before this is
this is not the moment for that
this is this is becoming an even starker
snitches it it is that i keep on coming
back to this metaphor but i just think
dr seuss was right
that um people in this case are choosing
sides
and it's it's masks or not it's mega
hats or not it's stars on your belly or
stars
or bellies without and uh and
it effectively reduces people to their
tribes it reduces people to their
demographic features
which is um oddly um
given this that this uh we won't wear
masks
uh groupthink
is coming out of the right it is a it is
using a demographic marker to identify
people exactly in the same way that the
social justice left has been using
demographic
markers to identify people it is just as
tribal
and just as grip thinking so i'm now
going to get myself into trouble
but i see a kind of analogy
there's a way in which people who
subscribe to a narrow version of liberty
right i want to be free to do anything i
want to do at any moment right
that kind of liberty um
there's a way that those people become
suckers they become pawns of this
corporate force that is you know
subtly enslaving us and
um the thing you know you said early
uh in our discussion here that the right
thing to do if you're sick is to stay
home and then you pointed out the
obvious fact that for most people
they know that that's not the rule
because they know
that their livelihood depends on keeping
their employer happy
and that their employee has a perverse
incentive where the employer
doesn't want the whole workforce to get
sick
but to the extent that somebody is sick
and capable of working frankly if the
whole workforce could work
sick and nobody is in a position to
prove that they got sick
at your establishment because you
incentivized your workers to come in
when they weren't well um that the cost
is externalized
they would be fine with it and so that
perverse incentive has
infected our whole economy such that
everybody who is in some kind of
jeopardy is depending
on their employer uh
feeling good about their work anybody
who is easily replaced because of the
nature of their work
or especially at least in the u.s given
our rather draconian
health insurance and employment rules in
place at the moment
if you're working less than half time
there's a very good chance that you're
hourly and not salaried and
you don't have sick leave and so what do
you do
if you need to pay the rent and you
and you what do you do
if you're actually at the level that
you're going to need the next paycheck
in order to
make it yeah and skipping out means
not just not just losing a day
but potentially antagonizing a boss who
has lots of other hungry people who
probably want this probably not very
well paying job
that doesn't come with sick pay sick
leave it's
it's a terrible terrible choice and
those of us who have lived most of our
adult lives
with either salaries or with enough of a
cushion
such that we aren't that close to the
border can
can sympathize and can recognize that
this is
a tremendous problem but have a harder
time actually
being in the space of having to decide
neither you nor i
have ever had to decide do i go to work
while i'm sick
because if i don't i may not have a
paycheck next month yep
neither neither of us has ever had that
position you know last time i worked
that kind of job was in college
but uh the the point i was heading
towards is that
the the
folks who um are attempting to maximize
narrow trivial liberties at this moment
are becoming the suckers who really
benefits
from us going back to normal and
polluting the data so we can't tell how
many people die and not worrying so much
about it and yes we're going to lose
people but wink wink they're old so they
were
on the way out anyway that style of
thinking
is actually i would say
in the interests of people whose
um economic establishments have been
idled but who themselves are in a
position
to insulate from the virus in other
words if you're living a cushy existence
and you've got you know you own uh some
i don't know fast food franchise
corporation if you're a partial owner of
that or you're a ceo of it or something
then the point is actually you don't
mind a certain amount of deaths among
the little people
in order to get stuff humming again and
if we've got to collectively rationalize
that there's really no death
coming out of this because it's not as
serious as we're claiming um
then so be it and so i have the sense
that these people who have fallen into
this
you know not only do we need to go back
to work
but we don't need to do it carefully
that
i would say knee-jerk mindset is
actually
cryptically the sort of corporate dream
here
is that we will stop obsessing over you
know the death of little people
in order for the economic machine to go
back to doing what it does
and um this is
also therefore a moment for us to
recognize
that we actually are in the same boat
and you know to the extent all of us you
mean all of us right
you're coughing on somebody because
you're confused about how dangerous this
is
then that cough you may be asymptomatic
you may cough on somebody they may
transmit it to somebody and somebody you
care about may die
downstream of that you may be doing this
to yourself and have no idea
um yeah so
um anyway the the the politicization is
really
the um the the frightening thing here
and i and i
i i feel compelled to say i know every
time
we take trump to task we are uh
we anger a certain fraction of the
people who
otherwise might be listening to us but
if there's one thing that i would say i
have not seen
broken during his presidency it is his
commitment to the political now you can
say
he needs to do that because the deep
state or
whatever is so frighteningly powerful
that this is the this is the only weapon
he's got but
i don't see it that way he is
politicizing this because it's the game
he is the master of right he's very good
at that game and you know if i had to
bet i'd say
he's going to win 2020 because he is
very good about it but
to politicize things at this moment is
actually
to create a tremendous amount of misery
and actually we have no way of guessing
how much it's going to be because
to the extent that more people get sick
because
of policies that are dismissive of the
danger
that gives the virus more landscape in
which to evolve and learn new tricks
we don't know if this is going to go
away in a year but you know we could be
stuck with this
permanently because it's learned new
tricks now
because his brilliance his genius if you
will is politics
um but he appears to be almost a
political savant
right he is he is so good in this realm
and he does not appear to know how to
surround himself
with advisors who are excellent in other
realms and to keep them
stably around him so if if that's right
and let's just don't throw that out
there is a possibility that he's a kind
of political savant
um we're left
we're left unfortunately in the position
that politics is inherently social
so just like again just like the social
justice
left uh that is mired the postmodern
left that is
mired in confusion about the nature of
reality and thinks that just by wishing
it true
they can create 87 sexes in all of this
garbage
you know having someone who's whose
primary if
not close to you know soul tool in their
arsenal is one that is social it's about
changing minds
that can't go up against a biological
reality like a virus
effectively he could get lucky he could
get unlucky so far it seems like he's
mostly gotten unlucky by making the
kinds of choices he has against this
virus
and it's none of none of the things he's
doing can
actually can actually respond directly
to it because he's wielding social tools
and it it doesn't care right it doesn't
care
about whether or not he changes people's
um
attitudes towards him and in fact
it's going to make it more powerful if
you know if if when lockdown
eases with lockdown easing
people are taking off their masks
because they think that masks make you
sheep and make you
not true not true americans
it's actually going to spread the thing
farther he's actually going to have been
working on behalf of the virus
yeah working on behalf of the virus is
exactly my thinking as well
and i think we don't have the proper
terminology
for the component of a hygiene
that is socially mediated maybe maybe we
do have a term and i'm just not thinking
of it but
the fact is when a person
uses the toilet and they do not wash
their hands
the chances of them causing themselves a
problem
are very close to zero but the chances
of them causing someone else a problem
are high the thing that causes you
to wash your hands is the shame
of taking that risk
which ultimately you know for those of
us who
had the right upbringing i guess it just
gets built in and you don't think about
it you don't
you know of course you wash your hands
and if there's no opportunity to wash
your hands you think i'm gone
you know what i'm doing like i'm walking
around with these
hands and i can't touch my face exactly
so um so there's something that just
becomes encoded it becomes
uh second nature and to have a political
entity whoever it is
right whether you know it's our
president or it's some
corporate thing that is itchy to get its
factory back online
that thing is creating the equivalent of
bad hygiene it may be
literally creating bad hygiene which
literally has
consequences for human health that are
unacceptable and
completely unnecessary i mean really
imagine that
this other this third position existed
and the third position was
there are some things we can go back to
doing right away there's nothing we
should be doing
exactly as we were doing it before
because even if it's safe today we don't
want to give the virus any extra
opportunity to learn tricks so let's be
careful outdoors even though the data at
the moment
suggests it's not likely to be
transmitted it's almost impossible
is what the data that we have currently
says so that
means hey you can take some extra
liberty here
here's a place we need to be extra
cautious i don't know what we do with
subway trains
public transit in general probably
that's not
a good idea to bring back online or if
you were going to do it you would want
to think about a very careful policy
about how
but that means that that sounds
impossible for many urban centers
for the vast majority of people who
again have high overlap with people with
with the group of people who are also
not salaried by hourly workers
who absolutely 100 depend on every
paycheck uh these are the people most
likely to be
depending on mass transit in big urban
centers like
new york london paris i agree
and i'm concerned that actually
um in part each side
is amping up something that is untrue
in an effort not to let the other side
get a foothold
and that standing down both
sides instinct to exaggerate is
necessary in our in order for us to
understand we work where we are
in other words covet 19 reveals
all sorts of things that were true you
know
last march before there was a cove at
19. march 2020 or march 2019
which last march 2019 yeah i don't mean
last march i mean
the march previous before presumably
this thing was
in the world uh in its present form
before it was
infecting human beings all of these
interconnected
pieces were true right people were
behaving
badly who had the flu it was killing
people's grandparents
it was something that they went to work
with
sometimes because they couldn't afford
not to
because feeding their family was a
higher priority to them than
uh the risk they put other people's
elderly parents and grandparents at
people were behaving badly with regard
to the flu everyone knows that the flu
kills people
and it is also true that so far as we
know
right now the flu is less transmissible
than stars go up to and has a lower case
fatality rate by
four or five times at least probably
right but if we look at what the new
york times did the other day and i must
say i'm very conflicted about it
that uh front page with the page of the
sunday new york times
in which they said um there are a
hundred thousand deaths
now in the us yeah right and they
went through boy they went through
papers and obits
across the country and just chose a
hundred a hundred a thousand names
and i don't know exactly how they did it
they didn't quite clarify um but they
i think they tried to choose across
various demographics geographic
sex race socioeconomics age especially
um and they just listed
the names the place of their death their
age and maybe a sentence about them
yeah phrase from from their obits
and it went you know it went i was
probably four or five full pages
of the front section of the new york
times above the fold and below the fold
on the front page of the sunday new york
times which is
you know was paper of record is
is by most measures still probably the
biggest newspaper in the world
yeah um so it was impressive it was hard
to ignore
well and it was an obvious allusion to
what happens
in a smaller disaster right an airline
crash there's the inevitable
list of the victims of the crash and
often there'll be pictures
after 9 11 they they did this i would
say actually it's an allusion to war
because you know pandemic and war are
are sister ideas
yeah i hadn't thought of it and and they
you know they come at you unexpected in
fact
um there's something in here i want to
read a little bit more but not right now
but
um i i think it's been a long time since
i read
camus the plague but this essay by
williams reminded me of it and i believe
that he
he makes that connection that um one of
the things about both
is that you don't see it coming there
are people with glimmers
glimmerings of it and there are people
who are preparing
and there are people who are mocking the
ones preparing yeah um
but when it's finally at your door it's
basically too late
to do any of the work that you might
have done in advance yeah it does
uh the even the style of the front page
um looked like a memorial wall
with just the endless list of names and
not very much information
but there was something about it that
didn't sit quite right with me
so on the one hand i think it is
important
to say you know how many airline crashes
a week is this the equivalent of if we
take all of the people the excess debts
how many airline crashes a week is it on
the other hand i find something very
disingenuous about the fact
that changes in policy very
frequently kill an airline airliner
worth of people
relatively quickly right we just don't
know who they are and we don't care
now we should care but we don't because
we don't have to
and if we did start caring at that level
we'd be overwhelmed by it so
the fact that this is like you know
easing environmental regulations
that cause more particulate matter to be
in the air in a particular place such
that more
children end up with uh later in adults
coming down with lung cancer
there's no way to track it for sure
right you just you you don't
know if any individual case of cancer
was due to those changes and regulations
early on
but too probabilistic yeah um so we can
say this number
died we can't say who they were because
even that can't be established or
things that create jeopardy that result
i mean you know
the thing that you were pointing at
about um the way people's lives are
hooked up
people a lot of people are close to the
bottom of the ladder
where if you fall just one rung too low
it's very hard to get back onto it i
mean once once you've become homeless
right once it's hard to get a shower
once you don't have multiple sets of
clothes and can't get them clean right
even if you had the skills to keep a job
it's very hard to get one
right so anyway how many people policies
that are
cruel with respect to taking people's
misfortune and allowing it to plague
them for the rest of their life and then
shortening those lives by leaving them
uh exposed to the elements these things
kill a lot of people
they don't get a new york times front
page listing their names
just because they died so there's a way
in which
i think the new york times is
broadcasting these names to give us a
sense of the magnitude of this crisis
and that is legitimate but in some sense
it invites a question about what else we
do
that is creating uh you know death and
misery
needlessly and what role good governance
would play in preventing it and
you know we talked in our last live
stream about
why the term progressive is not anathema
to us even though many of the things
that modern progressives
are advocating are not things we would
advocate
and the answer is we need progress we
are actually in mortal jeopardy if we
don't find it but
the the point i was trying to get to and
i think i've wandered from it but
covet 19 reveals the interconnectedness
and the difficulty
of good policy right we are now
all grappling with it in real time
because it affects whether or not we can
go out and get a cup of coffee right
but those things are in play 24 7
365 and decisions are being made
on our behalf by people who do not share
our interests
and they are having terrible
consequences they are creating
tremendous misery for people who did
nothing to invite it
and somehow the
corporate entity wants to talk about
covet 19
it has a perspective about what
it wants to occur but it doesn't want to
talk about the larger picture which is
what this reveals about
the needless misery and
interconnectedness of us
and the role that good uh enlightened
policy which actually liberates people
in
the rich sense of the term not the
narrow sense of the term
would look like the the the broad sense
of
enriches is that what you mean well i
and i've used this term
realized liberty i don't realize so
liberty the broad sense of liberty not
the broad sense of enriching
right no no i want people liberate in
the same way that i would argue
uh faa regulations liberate us to travel
and that that liberty is worth the
draconian regulations that allow
airplanes to be so damn reliable
that's an enlightened kind of liberty i
want the liberty that comes from the
regulation and frankly i want us to look
at the entire
the entirety of civilization this way i
do think liberty
is special and that in some sense it's
the only value that you can argue
to maximize but the reason you can argue
to maximize it
is because it integrates all the others
if you're sick
if you're poor you're not very there's
an understanding and a tracking of the
externalities
yes and if you actually had a proper
definition of it an enlightened
definition of it you'd find that when
you had maximized liberty
you would have solved all of the
solvable problems
that live beneath it in order to
liberate people you would have to
address these other concerns you'd have
to return the externalities and all
but that doesn't look like people going
out and coughing on one another it
really doesn't it just
it just doesn't um allow me to read
a couple of more short sections from
this uh thomas charlie and williams
article on the harpers a pandemic if you
are fortunate enough not to be
hospitalized or killed by it wears you
down by other more subtle measures
it administers by a thousand cuts a kind
of spiritual and psychological
incapacitation it sends you away on a
malevolent
holiday open-ended enough to make you
crave the rhythms and arters of labor
by stripping you of the most basic
knowledge that the world will remain
predictable
stable in the morning it makes you all
too aware of just how good you once had
it
and that no such assurance was ever
promised to you in the first place
and then later in the same paragraph it
is our great strength as well as our
terrible weakness to live most fully in
the past and in the future
but pestilences rob us of the sanctuary
of both of these states
forcing us into the totalizing
uncertainty and silence of the present
this struck me as so deep so that's
williams not camus
although it's emerging from his reading
re-reading camus
while in lockdown with his family and
they had the they had the foresight to
um they're in france to go into lockdown
with another family so
he's in the in the countryside in france
with two families with young children
but still um still enduring what
most of us in the world are enduring and
the idea
that we are all almost
all of us living in some moment that is
not now
is of course an idea that is repeated in
many spiritual traditions most famously
buddhism
right and the furthermore the idea that
a lockdown
slows time makes it hard to track time
makes us
all simply be in the moment for for
for much of it uh you know he he like us
um has has no immediate worry about his
own ability to feed his family
right he's concerned about how this how
this will play out for him and his
future and his livelihood he does
intellectual work and you know all of
this but
he's not worried about being on the
streets or starving for him or his
children or his family
um so those those concerns aside once
you deal with sort of that level of
maslow's hierarchy of needs
learning how to be present
with yourself to take in the sensory
information around you
is actually completely excruciating for
many people
and it is not something that especially
given the ghost of the machine that is
social media which is where you started
this
um but most people
by age adults seem to know how to do
to to be comfortable satisfied
being with themselves in the moment
without
certainty about what will come and this
is something that
we need to become able to at least
try to be in that space
all right several several things that
follow from that
um one i do think there's something very
rich
in the idea that a plague
forces you um
into some moment that has contracted
from both sides
right because the relevance of the way
you used to live
is not clear and where you're headed is
not clear and so you are sort of forced
into this
very narrow slice and it is
very jarring i think for all of us and
you know
i feel compelled to say as terrible as
this is
you and i are um just because of the way
we have
chosen to prioritize things in our life
we're very well situated
not for this not to drive us crazy i
think it's still driving us a little
crazy but no totally but we have birds
yeah we've got birds and lots of them
and um
but as a proxy for everything else
that's here right right
but um on the one hand
this ghost in the machine and the
machine i'm talking about is not the
internet
the machine i'm talking about is the
natural process that human beings use to
tune
into each other's thinking in order to
navigate novel circumstances like this
very odd pandemic yes right that machine
has a bug in it and the bug is the
internet
it's the platforms and their perspective
their
frankly absurd perspective that they
understand well enough
what the borders of reasonable
discussion are that they get to
intervene
and you know it's troubling enough
when they do this in plain sight and we
know for example that they've tossed
you know megan murphy off of twitter
because she thinks men and women are two
different things
right that we can see and we can we can
mock it enough that at least we retain
that piece of sanity right
many of us get that men and women are
different things and that it would be
absurd to banish somebody for saying so
but what we can't see are the subtle
biases right where they just put a
little shackle around the ankle of some
idea that they don't like and it doesn't
matter
the problem is often they will do this
because they're well
intentioned now it's still naive to
think that they know
what to shack what ideas to liberate and
amplify and what ideas
to uh to slow down but they will also do
it when they have a conflict of interest
because once they've built the mechanism
that corrupts thinking in a direction
that they think would be
noble then they have the tools to
corrupt thinking in a direction that is
lucrative
and there's no process by which that is
going to result
in them doing only those things that
they see are honorable bad as that would
be
they will do both and so to what extent
are we out in the world trying to
navigate this very confusing situation
ending up coughing on each other or
shouting at somebody as if they're an
animal to get them out of a supermarket
to what extent is this the consequence
of the fact that our natural conscious
process is corrupted
by this economic process on the outside
of it
that has effects on our thinking that we
can't begin to fathom
well i think you and i are in agreement
on this
and no we can't fully fathom it but i
will say
that
i know for sure that when
i have allowed myself to be free
of this ghost these ghosts in this
machine
or these machines for you know
it's it hasn't happened for more than a
couple of weeks at a time
in recent years back when we were doing
field research
my field site as you know because you
were there for one of my field seasons
with me
was completely remote and this was
before internet was was
much you know this was late 90s but
still um going and living in a tent in
the rain forest and a little island off
the coast of madagascar which itself had
not
a single movie theater in it even though
it's bigger than california
so really everyone was showering in a
waterfall
um spending days hiking the forest and
marking and studying frogs super remote
and it brings you it just focuses you to
this
okay well this is the this is the
research i'm doing we have to make rice
in order to eat
and we're you know if it starts raining
we have to bring our clothes
in under the under the tarp right we are
both still
traumatized every time we hear rain
start both of us
jump like what's that what is it what do
we have outside that needs to be
immediately pulled under cover yeah
exactly um and you know and more in
since basically since we started
evergreen since we've had children which
happened you know very quickly one after
another
i've managed to do um several week
study abroad and we did this final 11
week study abroad which still
because we were to hub in and out of
quito we would only have a week
uh really 10 days at the most without
any connection to the internet and then
back again
but even those 10 days is enough to
remind you
how different your brain looks when
you're not constantly being dragged
by forces that are actually economic
and we had this experience most recently
in january of this year which i
cannot believe that was this year but
when you know when we were
actually back in the most remote spot in
the ecuadorian amazon that
um that i've seen and it's extraordinary
and we were
tippatini for what 12 days which has no
internet
and it was glorious
it was but um many various things to say
one is when we used to go to madagascar
and i was only there for one field
season but we
i went three times yes four times um we
used to
tell our families you'll see us in
three months yeah you know and they
would say
can you please arrange to call us at
some point in the middle and we would
say no because it was so
difficult to actually make a phone call
off the island at that point
that even you know if we stood in line
at the telephone office
we might wait an hour and it might not
work anyway so we just wouldn't do it
however the problem is that the ghost in
the machine
is growing more powerful and more
mysterious by the hour
and so even the difference you know i
remember
i used to love taking students to dry
falls
in eastern washington and at first it
was very hard to get
cell service out there which was great
because all the students whether they
liked it or not were liberated from this
corruption and then it crept in but for
a little while
uh you could only get cell services if
you climbed on top of some
some difficult to climb rocks so it sort
of enforced
enforced a little bit of interesting
physical risk-taking to
get your cell service that you wanted so
badly yes and then very stupid
risk-taking because you're standing on
top of some rock outcropping on a cell
phone and it's very easy to
absent-mindedly
lose track of where you are and and that
could be terrible but which
never happened never happened but it
could have um but you know i will say
you know i i'm almost embarrassed for
planet earth to report the following
thing
but our last trip to tipputini
completely broke
our connection to the world as we knew
that it would
that said there is a canopy tower that
sticks up
from this literally the most diverse
habitat on earth
about as remote as you can get there's a
canopy tower it's about 130 feet in the
air i think yep
except above the canopy and
employees of the field station could
contact their families by climbing the
tower
and you know they had to have a
particular cell phone carrier there's
one antenna that was just
barely in range and you know for them i
get it they're staying in touch with
their families it makes total sense to
me
these are guys who are working i mean
they're being well treated by the field
station but they're working
what i think it's like it's something
like three weeks on one week off so they
get to see their families one week a
month
and uh it's let's you know a many hour
boat ride
up the river to see them it's not like
they can just pop in yeah
so i get it but and yet
yet the point is you're not going to be
safe from
this menace to your thinking anywhere
right
and even if you can make yourself you
know you can with discipline
break your connection to it in order to
figure out how you independently think
in
isolation from it but the problem is if
civilization is being driven crazy
by its connection then how much good
does it do you to be
sane in the midst of this spreading
insanity
all right um let's see there were a
couple other things
i wanted to discuss but maybe uh we'll
leave them
for another time uh yeah i mean i guess
the one that's relevant here
is i heard uh a friend pointed me to
joe rogan's conversation with david
pakman
and in that conversation they wrestle
with the question of
uh david is reporting that he was out on
his bike or maybe running or maybe both
and same time probably not at the same
time
um but anyway he was reporting how he's
using his mask and basically he's ended
up somewhere like you and i have where
you know yes masks he has it with him
when he's outside but he's not wearing
it unless
someone comes real close yeah or not
when he's biking hard or something like
that
and rogan uh
is disbelieving of the evidence that
actually this is difficult to transmit
outdoors and so his point is actually
i don't see any reason why droplets
shouldn't um be dangerous to you if
you're
walking behind somebody runs by you and
they exhale some droplets why shouldn't
that be as dangerous as anything else
and i think that this is emblematic of
exactly where we are
right first of all rogan's instinct
is exactly your in my instinct this
ought to be true
the fact that it is apparently not true
isn't so surprising to us because we've
spent a lot of time thinking about
complex systems and biology and this
kind of surprise
is you know it's the norm right things
that don't behave the way you expect
them to behave
you know you look at a tropical forest
and you think look at
all of this diversity and growth this
must be tremendously rich soil
no incredibly poor soil in general right
huh how does such poor soil give rise to
such
beautiful and aggressive diversity on
top of it well actually
like all paradoxes it's not a real
paradox the forest
is what it is and it has sucked the
nutrients out of the soil leaving it
barren right the competitors are so
strong that they've depleted the soil
that's the answer but
in any case to joe's point this ought to
be dangerous to us outdoors
apparently it isn't if the data and the
data comes from multiple sources now
if the data is what we think it is then
it is apparently at the moment still
very difficult to transmit outdoors
we ought to cherish that and protect it
rather than
disrupt it by treating it carelessly but
i think watching joe wrestle with the
complexity of this
joe you and i had a lot of experience
with students
[Music]
in various classes joe is like
the ultimate student right he's very
hungry to understand things
he's very broadly experienced he's got
nothing to prove
right very good at thinking
joe rogan is becoming confused about
covet 19.
why is he becoming confused i think he's
becoming confused because there is
so much of this politics and it is
infused into the ghost
in all of our machines and it is making
it impossible for people who
in general do a very good job of
thinking carefully to figure out what to
pay attention to
and what to dismiss it's doing it to all
of us you and me included
so anyway i just think there's a way in
which joe
obviously in some sense is the most
important media voice
in the world his uh decision to move to
spotify
is obviously not unrelated to this in
fact if we are to take
what alex jones reported about what joe
said to him
about why he was leaving youtube and
going to spotify
um this is about the corruption
and the danger of the power that google
holds over all of us right so this is in
some sense a rejection
of the ghost in the machine and i must
say
in that light i'm hopeful that actually
joe is going to accomplish what he's
setting out
to accomplish i'm hopeful and i think
it's actually more plausible than it
might seem
but that also leaves us with what to do
today dealing with this corruption of
our thinking
watching even those who in general help
us navigate the complex
failing to do a good job of it because
there's just too much pollution that's
the
that's the amount of gravity that
whatever force we're dealing with has to
it
and um you know
you and i have been arguing the biggest
danger to us is the politicization of
this
crisis i think um
that is turning into a prophetic concern
and it's not too late but it will be too
late if we don't do something about it
quickly so
especially given that this particular
weird perspective that the virus isn't
as serious as we think and masks aren't
necessary that that appears to be
a largely american confusion
let's take a step back and think about
how to be good to each other
and how to reason through this together
and
maybe we'll come out of it stronger
okay so we've reached the end of
this portion of the program we will
return in about 15 minutes
with a question and an answer we will
take your super chat questions we will
start with super chat questions from
this first hour
we'll get through as many as possible
and then we will move to the super chat
questions that come to us during the q
a there anything else we need to say
before we sign off for a few minutes
oh one correction from last time with
regard to i
said uh that we i had made a foia
request
a freedom of information act request uh
to evergreen and uh someone and i lost
it probably in all of the uploads and
downloads
of the episodes uh wrote in just to
point out
as you already knew it wasn't it
wouldn't have been foia which is federal
it was a um it was a public records
request yeah it's a public records
request so it's just a
small um but uh important legal
distinction
good and actually as long as we're in
that mindset i'm not going to explain it
now because we don't have
time to do it but something came across
my desk that caused me to adjust my
percentages with respect to the various
possible
origins of sars cove 2.
tune in next time yeah and next time i
will explain
what it was it actually came from a
viewer who contacted me alerted me to
something i hadn't understood
and it adjusted percentages not
radically but it greatly elevated one of
them and it reduced
uh another and i think it's worth
exploring it because the whole point of
doing the model with percentages was
that as new information changes your
uh your expectations uh you should
go through the formal exercise of
putting it on paper
right all right great we will see you in
15 or so minutes the link will be in the
description
you